<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/rfc2629.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2629 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3552 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3640 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3640.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' 
href="http://greenbytes.de/tech/webdav/rfc2629xslt/rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std"
     docName="draft-ietf-idr-registered-wide-bgp-communities-00"
     ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes=""
     updates=""
     submissionType="IETF"
     xml:lang="en">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->
  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

<front>

<title abbrev="registered-wide-bgp-communities">
Registered Wide BGP Community Values
</title>

<author initials="R" surname="Raszuk" fullname="Robert Raszuk"
role="editor">
      <organization>Mirantis Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>615 National Ave. #100</street>
          <city>Mt View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <facsimile></facsimile>
        <email>robert@raszuk.net</email>
        <uri></uri>
      </address>
</author>


<author initials="J" surname="Haas" fullname="Jeffrey Haas">
	<organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
	<address>
		<postal>
		<street>1194 N.Mathilda Ave</street>
		<city>Sunnyvale</city> 
		<region>CA</region>
		<code>94089</code>
		<country>US</country>
		</postal>
		<email>jhaas@pfrc.org</email>
	</address>
</author>

<date month="June" year="2015"/>
<area>Routing</area>
<workgroup>IDR Working Group</workgroup>
<keyword>I-D</keyword>
<keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
<keyword>IDR</keyword>

<abstract>
   
<t>Communicating various routing policies via route tagging 
plays an important role in external BGP peering relations. 
The most common tool used today to attach various information
about routes is realized with the use of BGP communities. 
Such information is important for the peering AS to perform 
some mutually agreed actions without the need to maintain a 
separate offline database for each pair of prefix and an 
associated with it requested set of action entries.</t>

<t>This document proposes to establish a new IANA maintained 
registry of most commonly used Wide BGP Communities by network 
operators. Such public registry will allow for easy refernece 
and clear interpretation of the actions associated with received
community values.</t>

</abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t><xref target="RFC1997">RFC 1997</xref> defines a BGP 
Community Attribute to be used as a tool to contain in BGP
update message various additional information about routes 
which may help to automate peering administration. As defined 
in <xref target="RFC1997">RFC 1997</xref> BGP Communities 
attribute consists of one or more sets of four octet values, 
where each one of them specifies a different community. Except
two reserved ranges the encoding of community values mandates 
that first two octets are to contain the Autonomous System 
number followed by next two octets containing locally defined 
value.</t>

<t>This document lists the most commonly used today BGP 
communities as well as provides a new registry for future 
definitions.</t>

</section>

<section title="Globally significant pre-defined values">

<section title="Well Known Standard BGP Communities">
<t>According to RFC 1997 as well as to IANA's 
Well-Known BGP Communities registry today the following 
BGP communities are defined to have global significance:</t>
  <texttable>
  
  <ttcol/><ttcol/><ttcol/>

  <c>0xFFFF0000</c><c>   planned-shut</c><c>  [draft-francois-bgp-gshut]</c>	
  <c>0xFFFFFF01</c><c>   NO_EXPORT   </c><c>         [RFC1997]</c>
  <c>0xFFFFFF02</c><c>   NO_ADVERTISE </c><c>        [RFC1997]</c>
  <c>0xFFFFFF03</c><c>   NO_EXPORT_SUBCONFED</c><c>  [RFC1997]</c>
  <c>0xFFFFFF04</c><c>   NOPEER </c><c>              [RFC3765]</c>

  </texttable>

<t> This document recommends for simplicity as well as for avoidance of backward 
compatibility issues the continued use of BGP Standard Community Attribute type 8 
as defined in RFC 1997 to distribute non Autonomous System specific Well-Known 
BGP Communities.</t>

<t>For the same reason the described registry does not intend to 
obsolete BGP Extended Community Attribute and any already defined 
and deployed extended communities. The new registry is to be used 
primarly for new community definitions in particular those which 
require to carry various new parameters or which should be propagated 
with a controled scope and radius.</t>

</section>

<section title="Registered pre-defined Wide BGP Communities">

 <t> It has been requested numerous times to have a globally unified way to 
 express some particular Autonomous System based routing policies. When defining 
 a new way to encode bgp communities we have an opportunity to define set of new 
 registered routing policies and route markings which could be passed within and 
 between Autonomous Systems resulting in their common interpretation.</t>
  
 <t> This document will request IANA to define and maintain a new 
 registry for pre-defined Wide BGP Community values. The allocation policy is on a 
 first come first served basis.</t>

 <t> It is recommended that an implementation supports by an 
 explicit enabling defined below Registered Wide BGP Communities. 
 Depending on the BGP implementation support it is recommended that an implementation 
 would support Registered Wide BGP Communities without breaking static or dynamic 
 peer/update groups. However it needs to be pointed out that support of all Registered 
 Wide BGP Communities is not mandatory. It will be perfectly valid for any BGP 
 implementation to support only subset of Wide BGP Communities.</t> 
  
 <t> It is strongly advised that each Autonomous System does an inbound verification 
 of received Wide BGP Communities from all of its EBGP peers before accepting them and 
 propagating within their own domain.</t>
 
 <t> The document does not mandate nor enforces that given registered type value 
 of Wide BGP Community would be of transitive or non-transitive type. It is for the 
 operator to determine the propagation AS radius required for such community when 
 appending it to routing information. However the document will provide a transitivity 
 radius recommendation to defined communities.</t>
 
 <t>The following Wide BGP Communities have global significance 
 and their execution should be uniformly implemented by any BGP 
 speaker supporting given set of Wide BGP Communities.</t>
 
 <t>The defined below value of the community should be interpreted 
 as registered value only if "R" - registered bit is set in the 
 community Type 1 container as described in [draft-raszuk-wide-bgp-communities] 
 Otherwise the value is local and it's actions is locally defined by the operator.</t>

  <section title="General Registered Wide BGP Community Values">

  <t>The below set of communities will be defined to be carried 
  in Wide BGP Community Type 1, with the container type values 
  (Community Registered Value) as per <xref target="iana"/>.</t>

<figure title='Figure 1: Wide BGP Community Type 1'>
<preamble></preamble>
<artwork align='center'>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            0x0001             |R C 0 0 0 0 0 0|   Hop Count   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Length             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                  Registered Community Value                   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Source AS Number                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                       Context AS Number                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Wide Community Target(s) TLV (optional)            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        Wide Community Exclude Target(s) TLV (optional)        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          Wide Community Parameter(s) TLV (optional)           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
Description format:

TYPE:  
    0x0001 (constant for this registry)
FLAGS "F":
    R - Registered bit (Set to 1 for registered values)
    C - Confederation bit (Set when applicable)
HOP COUNT "H":
    Defines domain or sub-domain propagation radius
LENGTH "L":
    Length of the Container Type 1 in octets
REGISTERED COMMUNITY VALUE "R":
    Value of the community in registry
SOURCE AS "S":
    Originator AS of Wide BGP Community
CONTEXT AS "C":
    For registered communities carries predefined meaning 
    or otherwise should be set to 0x00000000 
TARGET TLV "T":
    Set of atoms containing targets for execution
EXCLUDE TARGET TLV "E":
    Set of atoms containing excluded targets for execution
PARAMETER TLV "P":
    Set of atoms containing optional parameters for execution
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>   

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>  
BLACKHOLE
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = none
    L = 18 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - All transit traffic to destinations for which 
  advertised routes carry such community value should be dropped. 
  It is recommended that specified Autonomous System number should 
  be eligible and verified by BGP Origin Validation functionality to 
  advertise given BGP destinations.</t>
  
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
SOURCE FILTER
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = none
    L = 18 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - All transit traffic which source addresses have 
  been tagged by such Wide BGP Community should be dropped.</t>
  
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
SOURCE DO RPF
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = none
    L = 18 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none 
 </artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - All transit traffic which source addresses have 
  been tagged by such Wide BGP Community should be subject to Reverse
  Path Forwarding check when crossing Autonomous System boundaries.
  Source Autonomous System number specified in the body of this 
  community should directly indicate the peering interfaces on which 
  such RPF check should be performed.</t>
  
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
HIGH PRIORITY PREFIX
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = 0x00                    T = none
    L = 18 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - BGP prefixes carrying such Wide BGP Community 
  should be advertised to restarting peers before other prefixes 
  received by given BGP speaker.</t>
  
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
ATTACK TARGET
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = none
    L = 18 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - The ATTACK_TARGET Registered Wide BGP Community
  indicates that BGP prefixes carrying such community are receiving 
  unusual amount of unwanted traffic most likely due to some form of 
  network attack. Network devices capable of analyzing and mitigating
  such attacks can use such community as a hint on what destinations 
  to focus the most.</t>
  
</section>
  
<section title="Advertisement control Registered Wide BGP Communities"> 

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>  
NO ADVERTISE TO AS
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = Type_1 (Peer_AS)
    L = 25 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>

  <t>DESCRIPTION - All routes received which carry such Wide BGP
  Community containing this value MUST NOT be advertised to BGP 
  peer which Autonomous System number has been listed in the 
  TARGET TLV field of this community.</t>
  
  <t>Semantically specifying the reserved Autonomous System value 
  of 0xFFFFFFFF (ANY AS) would be an equivalent of using NO_ADVERTISE
  Well-Known Standard BGP Community Attribute.</t>

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork> 
ADVERTISE TO AS
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = Type_1 (Peer_AS)
    L = 25 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>

  <t>DESCRIPTION - All routes received carrying such Wide BGP Community 
  containing this value MUST ONLY be advertised to BGP peers which 
  Autonomous System number is specified in the TARGET TLV field of this 
  community. </t>
  
  <t>Semantically specifying the reserved Autonomous System value of 
  0xFFFFFFFF (ANY AS) would be an equivalent of advertisement to all 
  neighbors. Post execution this community MUST be removed.</t>

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
ADVERTISE AND SET NO EXPORT
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = Type_1 (Peer_AS)
    L = 25 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>  
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - All routes received carrying such Wide BGP 
  Community containing this value MUST be advertised to BGP 
  peer which Autonomous System number is specified in the TARGET TLV 
  field of this community with NO_EXPORT Standard BGP Community 
  attached.</t>
  
  <t>Semantically specifying in TARGET TLV the reserved Autonomous 
  System value of 0xFFFFFFFF (ANY AS) would be an equivalent of 
  advertisement to all neighbors with NO_EXPORT community being set. 
  Post execution this community MUST be removed.</t>
 
</section>
  
<section title="AS source marking Registered Wide BGP Communities">    
  
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>  
FROM PEER
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = 0x00                    T = none
    L = 18 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>

  <t> DESCRIPTION - Autonomous System may attach this community to 
  routes received from their EBGP peers to later, when advertising them
  outside the domain, apply or relax local policies only on such group 
  of destinations.</t>
  
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
FROM CUSTOMER
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = 0x00                    T = none
    L = 18 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>  
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - Autonomous System may attach this community to
  routes received from their customers to later, when advertising them
  outside the domain, apply or relax local policies only on such group 
  of destinations.</t>

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
INTERNAL
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = 0x00                    T = none
    L = 18 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>

  <t> DESCRIPTION - Autonomous System may attach this community 
  to routes originated in their own domain to later, when advertising
  them outside the domain, apply or relax local policies only on such 
  group of destinations.</t>

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
FROM UPSTREAM
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = 0x00                    T = none
    L = 18 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - Autonomous System may attach this community to 
  routes received from their EBGP upstream peers to later, when 
  advertising them outside the domain, apply or relax local policies 
  only on such group of destinations.</t>
  
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
FROM IX
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = 0x00                    T = none
    L = 18 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - Autonomous System may attach this community to 
  routes received from their EBGP peering sessions with the Internet
  Exchange peers or with Route Server to later, when advertising them 
  outside the domain, apply or relax local policies only on such 
  group of destinations. </t>
  
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
LEARNED FROM AS
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = 0x00                    T = Type_1 (Peer_AS)
    L = 25 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - Autonomous System may attach this community to 
  routes received from their EBGP peer by explicitly tagging them  
  with their peer's Autonomous System number as a value of the 
  TARGET TLV field. If the AS number is a two octet number first 
  two octest will be filled with zero. It is possible to use this 
  to also carry private AS number of customers.</t>

</section> 
  
<section title="Return path influencing Registered Wide BGP Communities">  
  
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
PATH HINT
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = Type_1 (AS#)
    L = 25 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - Autonomous System receiving such Wide BGP Community
  value should prefer for BGP prefixes received with such community 
  (for example by increasing value of local preference on ingress), a 
  BGP path which traverses Autonomous System number which has been 
  specified in the TARGET TLV field of this community. Post execution 
  this community SHOULD be kept.</t>

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
NEGATIVE PATH HINT
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = Type_1 (AS#)
    L = 25 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - Autonomous System receiving such Wide BGP Community
  value should prefer for BGP prefixes received with such community 
  (for example by increasing value of local preference on 
  ingress), a BGP path which DOES NOT traverses Autonomous System number 
  which has been specified in the TARGET TLV field of this community.
  Post execution this community SHOULD be kept.</t>
  
</section>
  
<section title="AS_PATH modifying Registered Wide BGP Communities">  
 
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork> 
PREPEND N TIMES BY AS
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = Type_1 (AS#)
    L = 29 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = Type_4 (0xAA)
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - The Autonomous System specified in the TARGET TLV 
  field of such community should prepend N times (encoded as 0xAA) its
  own Autonomous System number when advertising routes tagged with 
  this community to peers. Number of requested AS prepends is provided 
  in the PARAMETERS TLV field value. Post execution this community MUST 
  be removed.</t>
  
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>  
PREPEND N TIMES TO AS
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = Type_1 (AS#)
    L = 29 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = Type_4 (0xAA)
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - The Autonomous System advertising routes externally
  should prepend N times (encoded as 0xAA) its own Autonomous System 
  number when advertising routes tagged with this community to peer 
  which AS number is defined by TARGET TLV field. Number of requested 
  AS prepends is provided in the PARAMETERS TLV field. Post execution 
  this community MUST be removed.</t>

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>  
REPLACE BY
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = Type_1 (AS#)
    L = 25 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = none
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t>DESCRIPTION - All routes marked with such community advertised
  by an Autonomous System to all of its external peers should
  have any occurrence of an Autonomous System number specified in the 
  TARGET TLV field replaced with advertising domain's local Autonomous 
  System number. Post execution this community MUST be removed.</t>
		
</section>
  
<section title="Local Preference Registered Community">  

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
LOCAL PREFERENCE
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = none
    L = 22 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = Type_4 (ABBBBBBB)
    
    SEMANTICS of PARAMETERS TLV
        1 octet 1st bit indicates: 
            0-increment, 1-decrement
            7 bits - value of local preference value 1..127
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
				   
<t> DESCRIPTION - Autonomous System may suggest to its EBGP neighbor 
the following adjustments to the value of local preference as 
specified by given domain's local policy. The values of requested 
increment or decrement of local preference value is carried in the 
PARAMETERS TLV field. Post execution this community MUST be removed.</t>
	
</section> 
  
<section title="AS_PATH TTL Registered Community">  

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>    
AS_PATH TTL MAX RADIUS
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = none
    L = 22 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = Type_4 (0xAA) max AS_PATH radius
 </artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - Autonomous System may suggest to drop advertised prefix 
  by any transit network if its AS_PATH attribute length would be equal or 
  greater to encoded value both inbound or outbound of EBGP session. 
  The value of max AS_PATH length allowed is specified in the PARAMETERS TLV 
  field of the community. Post comparison this community MUST be kept.</t>
  
</section> 

<section title="GEO-LOCATION Registered Community">

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
GEOGRAPHIC LOCATION WHERE BGP ROUTE IS INTRODUCED TO AS
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = Operator's defined      T = none
    L = 26 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = Type_8 (5 UTF-8 characters)
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
    					  
<t>DESCRIPTION - Autonomous Systems may attach this community to routes
received from EBGP neighbors or introduced to BGP by other routing protocols
to identify the geographic location where the route was introduced to the AS.
The "right-most" two octets of PARAMETERS TLV correspond to an ISO3166-1 alpha-2
country identifier, while the "left-most" three octets may express a more
specific geographic location, such as a city or IXP encoded in 3 octets.</t>

<t>Example:</t>

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
Wide BGP Community describing route learnt by the AS at London, GB
     HOP COUNT - operator defined
     LENGTH - 26
     PARAMETERS - 3 octets locality string + 2 octets country id.
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork align='center'>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            0x0001             |       0x80    |      0xFF     | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            0x001A             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         IANA assigned                         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           0x000000AS                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           0x00000000                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      0x08     |            0x0008             | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       "L"     |       "O"     |       "N"     |      "G"      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       "B"     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>

</section>

</section>
</section>

<section title="Example"> 

<t>Customer of the source AS number 100 requests to execute AS_PATH prepend 
4 times when advertising the prefixes to AS number 2424. We will use the 
following community assigned on ingress or at the prefix origination. </t>

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>
PREPEND N TIMES TO AS
    Type: 0x0001                S = 0x00000064 (dec 100)
    F = 0x80                    C = 0x00000000
    H = 0x00                    T = 0x00000978 (dec 2424)
    L = 0x001D (dec 29 octets)  E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = 0x04 (dec 4)
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>  
  
<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork align='center'>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            0x0001             |       0x80    |      0x00     | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            0x001D             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         IANA assigned                         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           0x00000064                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           0x00000000                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      0x01     |            0x0007             | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           0x00000978                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      0x04     |            0x0004             | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      0x04     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>

</section>

<section title="ECMP Hint Registered Community">  

<figure><preamble></preamble><artwork>    
AS_PATH TTL MAX RADIUS
    Type: 0x0001                S = src AS #
    F = 0x80                    C = publisher AS #
    H = Operator's defined      T = none
    L = 22 octets               E = none
    R = IANA assigned           P = Type_4 (0xAA) max AS_PATH radius
 </artwork><postamble></postamble></figure>
  
  <t> DESCRIPTION - In multistage networks with large scale Equal Cost MultiPath (ECMP), it is often useful to separate flows towards a single destination among different paths along the parallel set at each stage. This wide community allows the operator to send a "hint" to the ingress router on how to set either the MPLS entropy label [RFC6790] or the IPv6 flow label [RFC3697] to achieve such flow separation. The Integer list given in the community can contain a label that is used by the receiver: Directly as an IPv6 flow label, Directly as an MPLS entropy label, As a seed used to calculate either a flow or entropy label</t>
  
</section>

<section title="Security considerations">

<t>All the security considerations for BGP Communities as well as 
for BGP Extended Communities RFCs apply here.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">

<t> This document requests IANA to define and maintain a new 
registry named: "Registered Wide BGP Communities Values". The 
reserved pool of 0x00000000-0xFFFFFFFF has been defined for its allocations. 
The allocation policy is on a first come first served basis.</t>

<t>This document makes the following assignments for the Registered 
Wide BGP Community values:</t>

<texttable align='center'>


<ttcol align='left'>Name</ttcol> <ttcol align='center'>Type Value</ttcol>
<c>BLACKHOLE                     </c><c>       1</c>
<c>SOURCE FILTER                 </c><c>       2</c>
<c>SOURCE DO RPF                 </c><c>       3</c>
<c>HIGH PRIORITY PREFIX           </c><c>      4</c>
<c>ATTACK TARGET                  </c><c>      5</c>
<c/><c/>
<c>NO ADVERTISE TO AS            </c><c>       6</c>
<c>ADVERTISE TO AS               </c><c>       7</c>
<c>ADVERTISE AND SET NO EXPORT  </c><c>        8</c>
<c/><c/>
<c>FROM PEER                    </c><c>        9</c>
<c>FROM CUSTOMER                  </c><c>      10</c>
<c>INTERNAL                    </c><c>         11</c>
<c>FROM UPSTREAM              </c><c>          12</c>
<c>FROM IX                    </c><c>          13</c>
<c>LEARNED FROM AS            </c><c>          14</c>
<c/><c/>
<c>PATH HINT                   </c><c>         15</c>
<c>PATH NEGATIVE HINT           </c><c>        16</c>
<c/><c/>
<c>PREPEND N TIMES BY AS        </c><c>        17</c>
<c>PREPEND N TIMES TO AS        </c><c>        18</c>
<c>REPLACE BY                   </c><c>        19</c>
<c/><c/>
<c>LOCAL PREFERENCE           </c><c>          20</c>
<c>AS_PATH TTL MAX RADIUS      </c><c>         21</c>
<c>GEO-LOCATION                </c><c>         22</c>
<c>ECMP HINT                   </c><c>         23</c>
<c/><c/>
<c>FREE POOL                   </c><c>       24..</c>
</texttable>

</section>

<section title="Contributors">

<t>The following people contributed significantly to the content of the document:</t>

<figure>
<preamble></preamble>
<artwork>
Bruno Decraene
France Telecom
38-40 rue du General Leclerc
92794 Issi Moulineaux cedex 9
France
Email: bruno.decraene@orange-ftgroup.com
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>

<figure>
<preamble></preamble>
<artwork>
Shintaro Kojima
OTEMACHI 1st. SQUARE EAST TOWER, 3F
1-5-1, Otemachi, 
Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo 100-0004
Japan
Email: koji@mfeed.ad.jp
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>

<figure>
<preamble></preamble>
<artwork>
Juan Alcaide
Cisco Systems
Research Triangle Park, NC
United States
Email: jalcaide@cisco.com
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>

<figure>
<preamble></preamble>
<artwork>
Burjiz Pithawala
Cisco Systems
170 West Tasman Dr
San Jose, CA
United States
Email: bpithaw@cisco.com
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>

<figure>
<preamble></preamble>
<artwork>
Saku Ytti
TDC Oy
Mechelininkatu 1a
00094 TDC
Finland
Email: ytti@tdc.net
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>

<figure>
<preamble></preamble>
<artwork>
Paul Jakma
School of Computing Science, Uni. of Glasgow
Sir Alwyn Williams Building
University of Glasgow
Glasgow 
G1 5AE
UK
Email: paulj@dcs.gla.ac.uk
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>

<figure>
<preamble></preamble>
<artwork>
Russ White
Ericsson
Oak Island, NC  28465
USA
Email: russw@riw.us
</artwork>
<postamble></postamble>
</figure>

</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">

<t>Authors would like to thank Enke Chen, Pedro Marques, Alton Lo 
and Jeff Wheeler for their valuable input.</t>

</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
	  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271"?>
	  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4360"?>
</references>

<references title="Informative References">
	  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1997"?>
	  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1998"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4384"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4893"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5668"?>
</references>
</back>
</rfc>

